All right, now, y'all fresh niggas,
y'all gonna be in the cutting game.
Very simple.
I want you to take your knife,
get in them cane, make it sing.
Take the cane out, cut my tops,
clean the shucks off,
throw it on a pile for the planting game.
Now, them cane ain't gonna jump up and bite you.
Don't shy back.
Rocher, boys, Rocher.
custom. I wonder what you'll do without me. I won't stay idle. Good money. You don't have to
share your cooking with other people. You don't. Be good for your mother. Okay, Alonzo? Stay safe.
I will call his name that he is now. Mr. Northup, I have two gentlemen whose acquaintance you should
make. Mr. Brown and Hamilton. Sir? Mr. Northup, these two gentlemen were inquiring about distinguished
individuals and I was just this very moment saying Solomon Northup is an expert player on
the violin. He was indeed. Mr. Moon is being overly gracious. Well, take it into consideration
his graciousness. Your modesty, may we trouble you for a moment of your time to converse, sir?
Of course. A circus. That is our usual employee. The company currently in the city of Washington.
Circus too constricting a word to describe the talented and merry band with which we travel.
It is a spectacle unlike most have ever witnessed. Creatures from the darkest Africa
get unseen by civilized men, acrobats from the Orient
who contort themselves in the most confounding manners.
And I myself, in aid of Mr. Brown,
an internationally renowned practitioner
in the art of prestidigitation.
We are on our way thither to rejoin the company,
having left for a short time to make a small profit
from our own exhibition.
The reason for our inquiry with Mr. Moon.
Yes, we had just a devil of a time
in procuring music for entertainments.
Men of true talents are seemingly in short supply.
Thank you, sir.
If we could persuade you to accompany us
us as far as Washington. We could give you one dollar for each day's services and three dollars
for every night played at our performances. In addition, we will provide sufficient pay for your
return here to Saratoga two weeks from today. Welcome to Washington, Solomon.
Today? Not too much. Some say not enough. Solomon, $43 all to you. That is far more than my wages
a mountain. It's been a most profitable week. Cheers. Cheers. Cheers. Another. Gentlemen,
your generosity is extraordinary. And your talents are undeniable. To Solomon. Cheers.
Cheers. It's all right, Solomon. There's no shame in it. No shame at all. Too many libations?
Halfway there.
We won't hear it. We won't.
Let him sleep, Hamilton.
A good night's rest.
And tomorrow, tomorrow you will feel as well and refreshed as if the Earth were new again.
Hamilton, there's nothing more we can do for him.
Well, boy, how you feel now?
My name, my name is Solomon Northam.
I'm a free man, a resident of Saratoga, New York,
the residence of my wife and children, who are equally free.
And you have no right whatsoever to detain me.
You're not any free man.
And I promise you, I promise you upon my liberation,
I will have satisfaction for this wrong.
Resolve this.
Produce your papers.
You're no free man.
And you ain't from Saratoga.
You're from Georgia.
You ain't a free man.
You're nothing but a Georgia runaway.
You're just a runaway nigger.
You a slave?
Yours is just rags and tatters.
You need something proper to wear.
Rags and tatters, rags and tatters.
Come on, wash up.
The boy too, get him clean.
Scrub now.
You know my mama will come?
Then hush him up.
Mama, mama.
Hush him up.
We need a sympathetic ear, an opportunity
to explain our situation.
Who, in your estimation, is that sympathetic ear?
The two men I journeyed with.
I'm certain they're making inquiries at this very moment.
I'll be just as certain they're counting the money paid
for delivering you to this place.
They were not kidnappers.
They were artists, fellow performers.
You know that?
You know for certain who they were?
The reality to come is us being transported southward.
New Orleans, if I was to venture, after we arrive,
will be put to market.
And beyond that, well, I suppose once in a slave state,
there's only one outcome.
No.
I don't say that to give you empty agitation, John.
For y'all, for y'all, there ain't nothing but the help
of John Wilson kidnapped.
John's just being held as dead, that's all.
Master, please, let John be redeemed.
Boy, our masters will not come for us.
John, John, I'm sorry for y'all,
but that's how it be where you're going.
You're going without John.
Mama, Brad.
Come on, get up.
I said get up.
No, no, don't.
Now, I don't want to hear you talk.
Get in the yard.
Not my children.
Ain't no need for all that.
Just taking a little trip.
That's all.
Don't want to frighten the children over a little boat
ride, do you?
That master's going to pay his debt.
Line up.
This master's going to pay his debt.
I don't want to hear a word out of none of you.
Not a one.
Come on.
Move.
Follow your mama.
Come on, boy.
Come on.
Up you step.
of that wagon. Come on. Come on, move it. Let's go, come on. Up the stairs. Come on, let's go.
Come on, move it. All right, come on. Hey, you, go on, get up. Sit down right there.
Right there, sit down. Cheer and don't be so cast down. If you want to survive, do and say as little
as possible tell no one who you really are and tell no one you can read and write unless you
want to be a dead nigga your mouth shut we're well planned i believe they could be strong
three can't go against the whole crew the rest here are niggas born and bred slaves
niggas ain't got no stomach for a fight not a damn one boss i know we get we were traveling
We wish we'd die trying.
Survival's not about certain death.
It's about keeping your head down.
Days ago, I was with my family in my home,
telling no one who I am.
That's the way to survive.
Well, I don't want to survive.
My solicitor has documentation verifying
the negro known as Clemens Ray is my property.
I know nothing of this arrangement.
You are ordered to return that property immediately
or be charged with thievery.
Free him!
Mr. Parker.
Ah, Mr. Northup.
Mrs. Northup.
Solomon, could I interest you in a new cravat?
Pure silk by way of the French.
We're in need of a fresh carry-off.
My missus is Travis. Nothing more.
The year has passed already.
Off to work at Sandy Hill again?
I am. I have just the thing.
Something to suit your style,
and yet sturdy enough for the 40-mile round trip.
It's beautiful. At what price?
We will take it.
Come see what your father has just purchased for me.
One moment, sir, and you'll be assisted.
Mr. Parker, sir, if we could discuss the pricing.
Forgive me, Solomon.
Mrs. Northup, a customer waits.
Welcome, sir.
Shop well, sir, but mind your wallet.
Pay no attention to this gentleman's nonsense.
Jesper!
My regrets for the intrusion, sir.
No intrusion.
Good day, sir.
Good day.
Jesper.
Very good, very good.
Let's see here.
Eliza!
Stand up when you hear your name. Eliza, Leffy, John, Oren, Platt. Stand up.
You fit the description given. Why didn't you answer when called?
My name's not Platt. My name...
Your name is Platt. Captain, get these niggers to my cart.
I believe I have something very much to your liking in the back room. Follow me, please.
Yes, now, inspect them at your leisure,
but I ask you to pay particular regard to young Ezra here.
Incredibly sound limbs.
I have never seen anything quite like him.
And this marvelous creature. Can you believe it?
Hmm? To make a fine lady's maid?
Yes, madam.
So, inspect at your leisure,
take your time, help yourself to refreshments.
Gentlemen, what catches your fancy here?
Hmm? This boy?
Yes, open your mouth. Open wider.
Look in there. Never been sick a day in his life.
And I call particular attention to Martha.
She is an excellent pastry cook.
Ah, Mr. Ford.
Splendid seeing you, sir.
What catches your fancy? This lad is very brawny.
How much are the wands, Platt and Eliza?
Ah, yes.
1,000 for Platt.
Oh, this is a nigger of considerable talent, I assure you.
700 for Eliza?
My fairest price?
You would accept a note?
Please, sir, do not divide my family.
Do not take me unless you take my choice.
Liza, quiet!
You will have the most faithful slave in me,
the most faithful slave that has ever lived,
but I beg that you do not separate us.
Stop it. I will give you something to cry about.
Randall, come forward. Come, come, come.
Now, you see how fit this boy is.
You know, like ripe fruit.
May I take your stick a moment?
Observe this, Randall.
Jump, jump, jump, run, run, run.
Good. Higher.
Do you see this? Very likely, he will grow into a fine beast.
Ah, 600 for the boy.
Fair and final.
Done.
Superb. A moment, please.
Mr. Ford.
Eliza!
How much for the little girl?
No use for her. One so young will bring you no profit.
No, no, no, no. I cannot sell the girl.
There's heaps and piles of money to be made from her.
She's a beauty, one of the regular bloods.
Well, none of you thick-lipped, bullet-headed, cotton-picking niggers here.
A child, man.
For God's sake, you're not sentimental in the least.
Ah, my sentimentality extends the length of a coin.
Now, do you take this lot?
Mr. Fordo, do you pass on them all?
I will take the ones Platt and Eliza sold.
Eliza and Platt. Splendid.
Get her out of here!
Are they keeping something to cry about, you goddamn wimps?
Get the hell out of here, kid! Out now! Out!
Pleasure.
Bring all those niggers.
Two of them.
You got two.
Mr. Chapin.
This one's crying.
Why is this one crying?
Separated from her children.
Oh, dear.
Couldn't be helped.
Poor, poor woman.
Mr. Chapin.
Yes, sir.
Tomorrow you can take these two up to the mill, start them working.
For now, make them adequate, fix them a meal, and have them rest themselves.
Yes, sir.
Come on, now.
Come on. Don't dawdle.
Something to eat and some rest.
Your children will soon be forgotten.
Now, for all of you raw niggers that don't know,
my name is John Tibbets,
William Ford's chief carpenter.
You will refer to me as Master.
Now, Mr. Chapin is the overseer on this plantation.
You, too, will refer to him as Master.
So clap your hands.
hands like this come on come on clap your hands nigga run nigga flow nigga tall his shirt in two
run run the patty roll look at you run nigga run well you better get away that's right like you
mean it nigga run run so fast over his head and on his nest run run the patty roll look at you
Run, nigga, run, well, you better get away
Run, nigga, run, the patty roller gets you
Some folks say a nigga don't steal
I caught three in my cornfield
One has a bushel and one has a pack
One has a rope, it was hung around his neck
Run, nigga, run, the patty roller gets you
Run, nigga, run, well, you better get away
Hey, Mr. Patti-Roller, don't catch me.
Catch that nigga behind that tree!
Run, nigga, run.
The Patti-Roller'll catch you.
Where you better get away.
Run, nigga, run.
The Patti-Roller'll catch you.
Where you better get away.
I am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac,
and the God of Jacob.
When the multitude heard this,
they were astonished at his doctors,
And then one of them, which was a lawyer,
asked him a question, tempting him.
The creek is plenty deep enough to sail,
even with a boat full of load.
The distance from the work area to the point on the Ladder Bayou
is several miles by water fewer than land.
It occurs to me that the expense of transportation
would be materially diminished...
Materially diminished?
...if we used the waterway.
Are you an engineer or a nigger?
Let the man say his piece.
It's a scheme plenty of engineers have schemed similarly.
The passes are too tight.
I reckon they're more than 12 feet at their most narrow.
Wide enough for a tub to traverse
if a team of niggers cleared it out.
And you know what of transport and terraforming?
I labored repairing the Champlain Canal
on the section over which William Van Nortwyk
was superintendent.
With my earnings, I hired several efficient engineers
hands to assist me and ended into contracts for the transportation of large rafts of timber from
lake champlain to troy well i'll admit to being impressed even if you won't collect the team and
see what good you can do all right
Let's clear it up.
One, two, three, four.
Hey, boy.
I'm fat.
I'm strong.
Yes.
I'm tall.
Yes, sir.
Flat, you are a marvel.
What took you so long?
Thank you, Master Voight.
Oh, thank you.
Yeah.
All right, marvel.
Yes, sir.
Yeah, sir.
All right, we're good.
All right.
Yeah.
Whoo!
I'll beat that.
Oh, that's a pleasant ending, yeah.
Oh, plaid.
My great thanks, Master Ford.
My thanks to you.
It is the least of it.
I hope it brings us both much joy over the years.
Stop your wailing.
You let yourself be overcome by sorrow, you will drown in it.
Have you stopped crying for your children?
You make no sounds, but will you ever let them go in your heart?
That's my flesh.
Then who is distressed?
Do I upset the master and the mistress?
Do you care less about my loss than their well-being?
Master Ford is a decent man.
He is a slaver.
Under the circumstances.
Under the circumstances, he's a slaver.
Will you truckle at his boot?
No.
You luxuriate in his favor.
I survive.
I will not fall into despair.
I will offer up my talents to Master Ford.
I will keep myself hearty till freedom is opportune.
Oh, Ford, is your opportunity?
You think he does not know that you are more than you suggest.
But he does nothing for you. Nothing.
You are no better than prized livestock.
Call for him. Call.
Tell him of your previous circumstances
and see what it earns you, Solomon.
So you settle into your role as Platt, then?
My back is thick with scars
for protesting my freedom.
I accuse you of nothing I cannot accuse.
I have done dishonorable things to survive and for all of them I have been no better than if I had stood up for myself.
Solomon, let me weep for my children.
Whosoever therefore shall humble himself as this little child, the same is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven.
And whoso shall receive one such little child in my name, receiveth me.
I cannot have that kind of depression about.
But whoso shall offend one of these little ones, it were better for him that a millstone were hanged about his neck and he were drowned in the depth of the sea.
Amen.
Make them boards flush.
They are, sir.
Now, they is no such thing.
They are smooth to the touch as a yearling's coat.
Are you calling me a liar, boy?
That's all a matter of perspective, sir.
From where you stand you may see differently, but the hands are not mistaken.
Simply ask that you use all your senses before rendering judgment.
Oh, my, you are a brute. You are a dog.
And no better for following instruction!
I'll do as ordered.
Well, then you'll be up at daybreak.
You'll procure a keg of nails from Chapin and commence to putting on clabberts.
Yes, sir.
Make them boards flush.
When I say I have my master's favor, you understand.
And for nine years he blessed me with every comfort and luxury in life,
silks and jewels and even servants to wait upon us.
And such was our life.
And the life of this beautiful girl I bore for him,
my Master Barry's daughter,
she always looked at me with an unkind nature.
And she hated Emily, no matter she and Emily were flesh or flesh.
As Master Barry's health failed, she gained power in the household,
and eventually I was brought to the city under the false pretense
of our free papers being executed.
Poor children.
I thought I told you to commence to putting on clapboards.
Yes, Master, I'm about it. These have all been replaced.
Well, didn't I tell you to get a keg of nails?
And so I did.
Goddamn you, I thought you knowed something!
I did as instructed.
If there's something wrong, it's wrong with the instruction.
with the instruction.
Bastard.
Goddamn black bastard.
Strip your clothes.
Strip.
Another day, nigga.
What is the matter?
Master Tibbies wants to whoop me for using
the nails you gave me.
I will have.
And I will have all of it.
Master, do not leave the plantation,
for if you run, I cannot protect you.
Stay here.
Whoever moves that nigger's a dead man.
I am the overseer on this plantation.
William Ford holds the mortgage on Platt.
If you bang him, he will lose his debt.
You have no claim to his life.
As for you two, if you have any regard for your own safety,
I say be gone!
You got no cause!
The plot is mine, and mine to do with as I please!
You touch!
Get Master Ford!
Long as they fear him, I don't believe you will remain passive at Tibby to tax.
I have transferred my debt to Edwin Epps.
He will take charge.
I cannot hear that.
Before I came to you, I was a free man.
Trying to save your life.
And I have a debt to be mindful of.
And that is to Edwin Epps now.
He is a hard man, prides himself on being a nigger breaker,
but truthfully, I could find no others who would take him.
You've made a reputation of yourself.
Whatever the circumstances, you are an exceptional nigger, Platt.
But I fear no good will come of it.
And that servant which knew his lord's will,
which knew his lord's will,
and prepared not himself, prepared not himself,
neither did according to his will,
shall be beaten with many stripes.
Did you hear that?
Stripes.
That nigger that don't obey his lord,
that's his master, d'you see?
That there nigger shall be beaten with many stripes.
Now, many signifies a great many.
40, 100, 150 lashes.
That's scripture.
What you got for James 295 pounds it's real good boy it's real good 182 for Platt
How much can even an average nigga pick a day?
200 pounds.
This nigga ain't even average.
512 pounds for Patsy.
512!
Your menfolk got no shame letting Patsy out pick you.
Day ain't yet come, she swung lower than 500 pounds.
You feel she is.
138 pounds.
I ain't done, Treech.
Ain't I owed a minute to luxuriate on the work Patsy done?
Yes, sir.
The lesson and the rewards of righteous living.
All be observant to that. All.
138 pounds for Phoebe.
Hit 145 yesterday. Pull her out.
206 pounds for George.
How much you pick yesterday?
229.
Come on, kid. Come on.
Come on boy move
We'll sell the niggas
sell little pants
She picked with more vigor than any other nigga choose another to go no other
Sell her or I'll take myself cuz I will read myself if you will before I do away with her. What you looking at?
I won't spoil it.
I will not.
Dance.
Dance is here.
Platt.
Yes, Mistress.
Can you find your way to Bartholomew's?
I can't, ma'am.
This is a list of goods and sundries.
You will take it to be filled and return immediately.
Take your tag.
Tell Bartholomew to add it to our debt.
Yes, Mistress.
Where you from, Platt?
Tell me again.
Washington.
Who were you, Master?
Master Namor Freeman.
Was he a learned man?
I suppose so.
He learn you to read?
A word, here or there.
But I've no understanding of the written text.
Don't trouble yourself with it.
Same as the rest, Master brought you here to work, that's all.
Any more, I'll earn you a hundred lashes.
Come here, boy. Come on.
Where you going, boy?
On my way to Bartholomew's, sent by Mrs. Epps.
You best get there, then. Get there quick.
Red and silver, and tobacco, two ounces.
Fool's cap paper.
Any trouble?
Epps, good Sunday morning.
Good morning, Master Shaw.
Master sent me to retrieve Patsy. May I approach?
You may.
Excuse me, Mr. Shaw.
Make a plan?
Patsy, Master wishes you to return.
Sabbath day, I was free to roam.
Master sent me running to fetch you.
Said no time should be wasted.
Drank your tea?
Thank you, mistress, but I don't dare.
Would you know Master Epps' consternation
to be any lessened with your time to return?
Anger's his constant condition.
Sit.
Sit and drink the tea that I offered.
Wouldn't be Epps' concern.
Better than I say.
Little gossip on the Sabbath be fine.
All things in moderation.
As you are aware, Master Epps is a man of hard countenance.
You know he has ill feeling towards your husband?
He do.
Master Epps has somehow come to believe that Master Shaw is
something of a Lothario.
A misguided belief, no doubt.
No doubt.
If not born out of truth itself, he ain't heard you.
Well, I'm in no disrespect to you, mistress.
Got no cause to worry for my sensibilities.
I ain't felt the end of a lash in more years than I can recall.
I ain't worked the field, neither.
Well, once I served, now I have others serving me.
the cost to my current existence,
be Master Shaw broadcasting his affections
and me enjoying the pantomime of his fidelity.
If that would keep me from cotton-picking niggers,
that would it be.
Small, at reasonable price, be paid for Shaw.
I know what it like to be the object
of Master's predilections and peculiarities.
A lusty visit in the night,
or visitation with the whip, take comfort passing.
Good Lord, he'll manage apps.
In his own time, good Lord, he'll manage them all.
The curse of the pharaohs, but a poor sample
of what wait for the plantation class.
This is nice.
That's it. That's it.
Do not look in his direction. Continue on.
That's it. Found him, Master.
Brought her back just as instructed.
What'd you just now tell her?
What did you say to Pats?
No words were spoken, none a consequence.
You're a liar.
You're a damn liar.
I saw you talking with her. Tell me.
Can I speak of what did not occur?
I'll cut your black throat!
Master!
You come here.
Master, I thought...
I said come here!
I brought her back, just like you.
Come here now!
Come on, come on, let's go.
I got it.
This is destructive.
Stay away from Pats, boy.
It's the Lord's day.
I don't know if the Christian and us care at all like this.
I could see it to you.
In the name of Allah,
I'll be master to his feet.
Master Epps!
What's the fuss?
Master Epps believed Patsy and me to be in conversation
when we were not.
I tried to explain, but it's led to all this.
What is it?
You can't remain the Sabbath without her under your eye?
Hold it.
You are a no-account bastard.
A filthy, godless heathen.
My bed is too holy for you to share.
What's he been telling you?
Of your misbegotten ways.
And he would know what of anything.
I ain't even spoken with him today.
You lying neger-plant.
Have I?
There.
There's all the truth he got.
Come sample what I baked for y'all.
Thank you, mistress. Thank you, mistress.
There'll be none for you.
You see that?
You see that look of insolence she give me?
Say nothing but...
It was hot, hateful scorn.
It filled that black face.
You tell me you didn't see it.
It's because you choose not to look.
Or you saying I lie?
Whatever it was, it passed.
They foul with their hate.
You let it be, it's gonna come back to us in the dark of night.
You want that?
You want them black animals leave us gut-like peeves in our own sleep?
A damn eunuch if they ain't.
If you won't stand for me, I pray you'd at least be a credit to your own kind and beat
every foul thought from them.
Eat!
Fill yourselves.
I said eat.
I have a request.
Kindness.
into my life take my body to the margin of the swamp take me by the throat hold me low in the
water until i steal and without life bury me in a lonely place i don't do no such thing
the gory detail with which you speak no i ain't got no comfort in this life if i can't
Bide mercy from you.
I'll beg it.
I'll be no hell for it.
Do what I ain't got the strength to do myself.
It's a plague.
It's damn biblical.
Two seasons God done sent a plague to smite me.
It makes me so burdened.
Eden's they are.
They brought me God's scorn.
I have you.
Judge.
On your steps.
I'm deeply saddened to hear about your misfortune.
The price don't reflect your concern.
Listen up, you're Judge Turner's for the season,
more if need be, till my crops return.
You don't bring no disrespect to me.
You don't bring no biblical plagues to him, you hear?
I'll take it out of your skin.
Get out.
Get out the porch.
You ain't supposed to be on the porch.
Cloud, is he?
Yes, sir.
He cultivate cane previously?
No, sir, I've not.
That comes to you quite naturally.
you educated also niggas are hard to work and i read all right you play the fiddle yes sir yes i
do willard yoni the plant up the bayou celebrates his anniversary in a three weeks time i'll hold
out your name to him what you earn is yours to keep mind yourself flat times is behind us
Clean livin' and prayer done lifted the plague
As thick and white as New England snow
Some of my niggas has returned to me
Where Judge Turner gave you favor
I'll implant with your slick nigger ways
Well, you won't stand idle, boy
Not on my land
Much work to do
Days of old, long since
Huh, Joyce?
Indeed!
Let's go find something sweet for you
Huh?
Oh, pick this cotton!
Man ain't mean, boys!
Oh, work this cotton!
Oh, work ain't hard, boys!
George.
180 pounds.
Patsy.
520 pounds for Patsy.
That's my girl.
Don't ever let me down.
Platt.
160 pounds.
Armsby.
64 pounds.
A day's labor would average 200 pounds.
Yes, sir.
It's a picker, but it takes effort, boy.
Put some damn effort into it.
Yes, sir.
Take him out.
Get to whooping.
It's a tragedy.
How does such come to pass?
Work in the field and picking cotton like a lowly hand?
I am of a damn sight better station.
I've worked as an overseer, you know.
I did not know, sir.
Not sir.
Just arms fee.
You know, I do more than any other in the field.
How did you arrive at such a place, if I may ask?
Ask, it's just a conversation.
I became a little too dependent on the whiskey,
a little too undependable on the job.
Now before you say I'm just a sorry drunkard,
just let me state my case.
As reliable employment as overseeing is,
it is no easy chore on the spirit.
I say no man of conscience can take the last
to another human day in, day out
without shredding at his own self.
Takes him to a place where he either makes excuses within his mind to be unaffected,
or he finds some way to trample his guilty sensations.
And I trampled with frequency.
I gave in to tales of wealth and prosperity.
Such profitable outcomes are reserved for plantation masters.
It's the lot of the rest of us to serve.
is to earn a decent wage and get myself home.
The proceeds of my fiddling performances,
just a few pick of humans,
but all I have in the world,
I promise them to you
if you will do me the favor I require,
but I beg you not to expose me
if you cannot grant the request.
Well, what is it you ask?
First, your word, sir.
On my honor.
It's a simple enough request.
I only ask that you deposit a letter
at the post office of marksville and that you keep the action an inviolable secret forever
i'll do it and i'll accept whatever payment's offered to assist you i put my own self at risk
i will do so but fair compensation is all i have draw up your letter we'll meet again in two days
tries to get white fellas to mail arms we told me today the devil was among my niggers needed
watching or he would run away when i asked him why he said you come over to him wake him up in the
middle of the night i wanted him to carry a letter to martville what'd i say to that i write a letter
without ink paper who am i gonna write to i got no friends living as i know of that arms be is a
lying drunken he wants you to hire him as an overseer wants to make you believe we're all
gonna run away so you'll hire him as an overseer he believes you're a soft soap and he's given to
such talk made this story out of whole cloth because he wants the situation were he not free
and white plant were he not free and white he picking boy i just want to say something
about uncle abe he was a good man and he always looked out for us ever since we were little
God love him, God bless him, God keep him.
Went down to the River Jordan
Where John baptized three
When I walked the devil in hell
Says, Johnny baptized me
I say, Row, Jordan, row
Row, Jordan, row
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord
For the year when Jordan rolled
Well, some say John was a Baptist
Some say John was a Jew
But I say John was a preacher
Cause my Bible says so too
I say roll, Jordan, roll
Roll, Jordan, roll
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord
For the year when Jordan rolled
Hallelujah, roll, Jordan, roll
Roll, Jordan, roll
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord
For the year when Jordan rolled
Hallelujah
Roll, Jordan, roll
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord
For the year when Jordan rolled
Everybody say roll, Jordan, roll
Roll, Jordan, roll
right to the end hey bass oh no no no no shame in taking respite from the heat drink shade
it's ungodly for travelers party or otherwise and what's funny eps i merely mean to finish
the work at hand as requested and as paid for something rubs you wrongly i offer you the
opportunity to speak on you ask plainly so i will tell you plainly what amused me just then
was your concern for my well-being in this heat when quite frankly the condition of your laborers
it is horrid the hell it's all wrong all wrong mr epps they ain't hired help
they're my property you say that with pride i say it is fact this conversation concerns what
is factual and what is not then it must be said that there is no justice no righteousness in this
slavery but you do open up an interesting question what right have you to your niggas
when you come down to the point what right i bought them i paid for them of course you did
and the law says you have the right to hold a nigga but begging the law's pardon it lies
suppose they pass the law taking away your liberty making you a slave suppose that ain't
in this supposable case.
Laws change, Epps.
Universal truths are constant.
It is a fact, a plain and simple fact,
that what is true and right is true and right for all.
White and black alike.
You compare me to a nigger, Bass?
I'm only asking in the eyes of God, what is the difference?
Might as well ask what the difference is
between a white man and a baboon.
I seen one of them critters in Orleans
know just as much as any nigger I got.
Listen, Epps, these niggas are human beings.
If they are allowed to climb no higher than brood animals,
you and men like you will have to answer for it.
There is an ill, Mr. Epps, a fearful ill,
resting upon this nation,
and there will be a day of reckoning yet.
You like to hear yourself talk, Bass,
better than any man I know of.
You'd argue that black was white or white black.
If anybody'd contradict you,
find supposition if you lived among Yankees in New England.
But you don't.
Most assuredly do not.
Where is she, Kevin?
Where is she?
Where is Pat?
What you standing there for?
We know nothing of her, master.
Know nothing of what?
We know nothing of her.
Of what?
Where is she going?
I don't know.
She run off, ain't she?
She run off.
Where is she?
Huh?
You know, you know, you know, you know, you know.
No, I don't.
Miserable black dogs stand like the deep and dumb.
Beak!
She gone?
Run off.
Run off, did you?
Mr. Epps.
You miserable wench, where you been?
I've been nowhere.
Lost your misdeeds.
Sabbath day, master.
I took me a walk to commune with the Lord.
Bring the Lord into you, deceptions.
You coming from Charles Plantation?
No!
Mr. Epps, no!
Now you speak.
Now it's what I had to holler as you find your tongue.
I went to Master Charles Plantation.
You admit it?
Yes, freely.
And you know why?
I got this from Mrs. Shaw.
Mrs. Lips won't even grant me no soap to clean with.
I stink so much, I make myself gag.
Pounds of cotton, day in, day out.
More than any man here.
And for that, I will be clean.
That's all I ask.
This here, what I went to Shaw's for.
The Lord knows that's all.
You're a liar.
And you, blind with your own covetousness.
I don't lie, mess.
If you kill me, I'll stick to that.
I'll fetch you down.
I need to go to Shaw's.
Treach!
Run, fetch some wine.
Edwin!
Strip her.
Strike her bear and lash her to the post.
Do it.
Strike the life from her.
Beat her. Give her the whip. Give it all to her.
Platt, you come here and you beat her now.
Platt!
You strike her.
He pantomimes.
There's barely a welt on him.
That's what your nigger's making you.
Fool for the taking.
Strike her, Platt! Strike her!
Her flesh is rent and meat and blood flow equal.
I will kill every nigger in my sight.
You understand me?
Strike her! Strike her!
Till I say no more, I ain't said nothing.
Course of eternal justice, thou shalt answer for this sin.
Sin? There is no sin.
Man does how he pleases with his property.
The moment planned. I am of great pleasure.
You be goddamn careful. I don't want to come a lot in my mood no further.
I want to ask you what part of the country you come from.
Where do you come from?
No part of this land.
I originate from Canada.
And guess where that is?
Well, I know where Canada is.
I've been there myself.
Montreal, and Kingston, and Queenston,
and a great many places.
Well, travel for a slave.
How came you here?
Mr. Bash, if justice had been done,
I never would have been here.
How's this?
Tell me all.
Afraid to tell you.
The word you speak is a profound secret.
The story, it is amazing, and in no good way.
Do you believe, sir, in justice, as you've said?
Slavery is an evil that should befall none.
I believe so.
You truly do.
Then I ask, I beg, that you write my friends in the North,
acquainting them of my situation,
and beseeching them to forward free papers,
would be an unspeakable happiness to see my wife.
Travel this country for the best part of 20 years.
My freedom is everything.
The fact that I can walk out of here tomorrow
brings me great pleasure.
If it doesn't mean much to anyone,
it seems yours might mean a lot to a whole lot of people.
But what you ask of me, sir, scares me.
I must say, I am afraid.
Not just for you, but for me.
I will write your letter, sir.
and if it brings you your freedom, it will be more than a pleasure.
It will have been my duty.
Now, would you kindly hand me those shingles?
There's a boy called Platt. Come here, boy.
Your name is Platt, is it?
Yes, sir.
You know that man? Say again.
Mr. Parker.
That man received a letter compiling many accusations.
You look me in the eye.
And on your life, you answer me truthfully.
Have you any other name than Platt?
Solomon Northup is my name.
Sheriff, what's all this?
It's official business.
My nigger, my business.
Your business waits.
Tell me of your family.
Platt, I have a wife, two children.
What the hell?
What are your children's names?
Margaret and Alonzo.
What was your wife's name before her marriage?
Ann Hampton, I am who I say.
Where are you going, Platt?
I'm going to authorize you to interfere with my property.
My authority.
Platt, you come back here.
Platt, you come back here, boy.
You will unhand him.
Platt is my nigger.
He is Mr. Solomon Northam.
You say you come here unfamiliar to me and make claims.
Not no doubt, sir. The man is Solomon Northam.
The hell he is. He's my nigger, and I'll fight you for it.
As is your right.
As it will be my pleasure to bankrupt you in the courts.
Your decision.
Unhand him.
I know you had some hand in this, Vlad.
I'm gonna get to the bottom of it.
Pay him no mind.
I paid good money for this nigger.
Courthouse got papers to prove it.
And we got papers proving he's free.
I own you. You belong to me.
You hear me, Vlad? Unhand him.
We'll have 200 shots across your back by sundown.
Get my horse, Treach.
Get away from him, Pats.
I'll be seeing you real soon.
Solomon, we need to make haste.
No.
Solomon.
He's my husband.
Very good to meet you, sir.
What you going to think to do?
And this is your grandson, Solomon Northupstone.
On to the river Jordan, where John baptized three.
When I walked the devil in hell, said, Johnny, baptize me.
I say, roll, Jordan, roll.
Roll, Jordan, roll.
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord.
Well, some say John was a Baptist.
Some say John was a Jew.
But I say John was a preacher
My Bible says so too
I say roll, Jordan, roll
Roll, Jordan, roll
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord
For the year when Jordan rolled
Hallelujah
Roll, Jordan, roll
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord